[SPEAKER_00]: There's loads of questions, anyway, that I'll start with.
[SPEAKER_00]: This Anupana Sutta, 118.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, the fulfillment of the Four Foundations of Mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you do breathing, it says,
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the being who abides contemplating the body as a body, ardent, fully aware, mindful, having put away covetousness and grief for the world, I say that this is a certain body among the bodies, namely, inner, outer, breathing, in-breathing, out-breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I say that it is a certain body among the bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's a...
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite a bit of a debate over that translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember Bhikkhu Bodhi and then, I think, Jnana Malatya, he was referring to it as a body of in-and-out breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then another said, well, no, it refers to the whole body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I said, well, no, it refers to the whole body of breathing or this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was never clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of the practice of the mindfulness of breathing, I think, maybe, maybe I didn't, but I think I mentioned that in the note citation, maybe you don't get that, didn't have that part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the mindfulness, yeah, the mindfulness of the in-and-out breath, in-and-out breathing is inseparable from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one doesn't occur with the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly conceive in-and-out breath of breathing without conceiving the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, body means breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're mindful of in-and-out breath, then
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is the body there at that time, is one among the ways of experiencing the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body among... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Among all the possibilities you can experience your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Familiar, unfamiliar, far, near, heavier, light, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is one of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the body of
[SPEAKER_01]: The way the body is experienced while breathing, while being mindful of breathing, not just left while breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have time to refine my vision of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that's because you're expecting to find something hidden there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to, like, sharpen your binoculars to really see the details.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is true only to a certain extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't really work like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sharpening the image means, like, clearing the vision, as you say, it means just finding more details about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can find as many details as you like, if you have no sight of the nature of that thing, which is on a general level, no details will help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, what do you expect?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you hope?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you crave for, to find, when you look at the body, when you want to look at it even closely?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's there?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what I expect, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I say, yeah, I want, okay, I'm going to look, be mindful of the body, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, just... well, to become dispassionate towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be passionate towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that a goal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is dispassion good?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to be free from that passion or depression, covetousness and grief of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are those covetousness, grief in the world and everything have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole point is to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your attempts to look at the body closer and closer and closer are frustrating you and making you suffer,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you're contradicting the whole purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, we agree, mindfulness of the body will bring freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to find out how.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just do it blindly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yes, we agree, not being mindful and not keeping the precepts will certainly result in pain and suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when it comes to... Because you are doing the suffering, the suffering is not hidden behind some
[SPEAKER_01]: Some distant, I don't know, stones that you have to all turn up and look underneath and find what's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you place yourself in certain amount of containment through precincts and kind of, okay, I practice, I'm making the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now within that, you actually have to sometimes turn around and look at what you're doing within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just keep going and looking out to find the cause of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because craving is done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And craving is the absolutely only direct... well, it's the direct and absolutely only cause for dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving means presence of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of craving is absence of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no time lapse in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a simultaneously arising, simultaneously ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever there is suffering in regard to absolutely anything, even if it's your meditation, means craving is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, certain amount of suffering is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you put that container, the craving is still there, so you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just keep taking that for granted, you'll never recognize the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, after a while, within that container, you have to start saying, okay, this is not me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not doing anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why am I still suffering within that?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you recognize that the claiming is that dārtha, that directly is generating suffering, you stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you'll know how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, by the way, ānāpānasati is taught to these sort of ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't mean you shouldn't be trying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, through trying that, you can, you know, come to understand these things I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you have to know that
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to keep a goal in mind, because it's so easy to become, when it comes to meditation and everything, and obviously, because all of the contemporary interpretations and techniques and stages and attainments or whatever else they talk about, you kind of are always led to expect something.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you go and sit, you expect something.
[SPEAKER_01]: I expect peace from meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I expect this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I expect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And expecting something, it's like waiting for something, doing it in order for something to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the type of wrong meditation that the Buddha condemned.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sutra, when he said, you're like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk premeditates, overmeditates, undermeditates, mismeditates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a hyena, like, waiting in front of a rabbit hole, or as a stork, like, waiting for the fish, just waiting and waiting, like, focusing just on one point, looking for other animals of prey, in the same sense, the monk sits and, like, waiting for something to happen in his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically meditation today.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where it's told as meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if it's not explicitly defined, you will inevitably imply that expectation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That expectation will be implied in whatever meditation you do, whatever meditation technique, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing they all have in common is, none of them will teach you understanding, because there isn't any.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll teach you a technique, they'll teach you a type of praying upon something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you pray upon something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it comes down to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, whether it's this, vipassana, that, you're just praying upon something, then you have this overwhelming feelings or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, I got it in a rose or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's all just, you know, you tickle your foot, it will start to itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you do this, it will result in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It absolutely means nothing in terms of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you have the understanding, even if you do meditation, you'll be doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whichever meditation you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you'll be doing it through the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I, from the perspective of craving, and not craving, and I'll generate more craving, and I'll be independent upon craving expectations.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you'll be, like, standing yourself even further in the path of non-suffering that you already understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know that suffering is... Because you know how suffering rises, you know how suffering ceases, so whatever you do, you'll be doing it for the cessation of that suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when I was... say, if I focus on that earth element, and seeing the earth element just... it's just the earth element,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing more that can be expected from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite, you know, in my experience, like I say, I establish a mind in this.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no...
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel like, oh, this is... it's just the earth that it moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: And establish your mind in that place.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing more that I can expect.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing that you can develop then, but I think that does not... it's not... cannot be done through craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, there won't be any expectation, there won't be any craving when you establish your mind on Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can do then is keep developing, practicing mindfulness in regard to the established mind upon Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, I mean, like, hold it in your mind for as long as you can, as they do in those vipassana centers or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But be aware of its persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: of the arising thing, which is establishment upon earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, there's nothing to expect here.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's still present, and it's still present, and it's still present, and it's still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not equally present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other things start arising, but don't lose the sight of that establishment, which starts to act as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there, while other things are arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you're really experiencing things through that foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Foundation of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why they call foundations or references or whatever else, you know, translated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will see that whatever, that thing upon which you're established, will eventually come to fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you're aware, you know, you see arising and ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's arising and it's cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said before, arising is like ascension.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation is like descent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's through arising, persisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through ceasing, persisting, while changing, is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why three characteristics, but they're not linear characteristics, as they are translated or usually written down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's arising while persisting, while persisting and changing, and it's ceasing while persisting and changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fading in, fading out.
[SPEAKER_01]: The identity of the same thing remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in a way, it's not the same thing, because its intensity varies, changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, another thing has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, with the establishment upon such a general phenomenon, such as Earth, or any other casino, you can just maintain that mindfulness throughout, in regard to anything, because anything that arises on a particular level, has the element of Earth in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the sublime, the most supreme of them all, casino of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that arises implies presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how subtle, how quick, how slow.
[SPEAKER_01]: You establish upon the phenomenon of presence of anything, your mindfulness cannot lapse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's actually maintained through the particular arising of various irrelevant things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that, sir, establishing your mind on infinite consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that be the same thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then it does seem a bit easy, easier, should I say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, because if you establish your mind on presence... Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't mean presence in a tree-hugging, new-aging... Yeah, just a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean presence, phenomenological presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a present of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it's in front of you, a thing that has a reason, it is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So within that, it's in front of you, you can be even more mindful and more established upon something more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can get a search upon the Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the element of Earth is present through other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite supreme in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there is more supreme in regard to the element of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ultimately, it's the Consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the most supreme, the most refined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't have to go that far, because it's that reference point that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what gets to me more, as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose, it's my craving, because I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I try to establish my own earth, and then, what is there?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just lots of water, and there's lots of fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about some air?
[SPEAKER_01]: How about some diversity?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then I think, okay, well... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that starts happening, it means you are not really established upon the element of earth, because you lost it so quickly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were established, if your mindfulness was set in it, then when those other cravings start coming up, you see them through this reference point, which you won't lose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you start feeling, oh, what if I start losing this reference point?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that through the reference point of Earth, because it is within there, already.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how understanding comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through practicing that, while...
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, I was emphasizing that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the practice of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: While two things simultaneously present, you become aware of that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you do that long enough, you realize that the understanding will come, even if you don't go around experiencing every individual thing that can arise while you're established upon the element of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do that to a certain extent, but after a while it becomes apparent, you understand, you see through it, and you realize that whatever has arisen, whatever will arise, whatever is arising now, will remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how that understanding kind of compensates, deals with it, fills up whatever else experience you were lacking in terms of insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sometimes you need to go through these motions more before the understanding occurs, but eventually it should occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it does, then you will stop chasing particular things and stop being concerned about them, because you understood
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever comes in, whatever goes out, has to come through at this point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if a particular thing never mattered.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was that relationship that you were not aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: It hasn't been understood, which was inducing all sorts of emotions and cravings and feelings and confusions and five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'll experience...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll be the experiencing rapture.
[SPEAKER_00]: I say that this is a certain feeling among feelings, namely giving close attention to in-and-out breathing, a certain feeling amongst feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, giving close attention, I don't know, like, we will have to really look into a file in there, see the translation, but anyway, I can still answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole point, the whole point, say, say you understood the craving, you soon found all the truths, so you, you are at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You practice mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, breathing is bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an intentional act that belongs to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with the lack of mindfulness and with the lack of knowledge, that bodily act is appropriated either through I am reading forcefully or voluntarily,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, through complete ignorance of that breathing, whereby you think it's completely automatic, so you obscure the fact that it is intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't do either, you can actually come to see that breathing is an intentional act being done right here, that doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there isn't anything more you can ask for, in terms of... in terms of a meditation object, inverted commas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have an act being done right here, right now, intentional act, not involuntary, like a heartbeat or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it doesn't belong to you, it belongs to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become established in that, then
[SPEAKER_01]: That body there will be one among the bodies which you're experiencing, but it will be the body that matters, it will be the body that is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That feeling there, looking at that type of intentional breathing that doesn't belong to you, that feeling you have there at that time in regard to that, will be one among feelings that you can experience, but it will be the one that matters, because it will be a feeling that is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That intention there, and we're saying for all the aggregates,
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it will have to, if done properly with the right view, it will have to culminate in the full development of the enlightenment factors, the four powers and then the enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we just reveal the whole thing as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it has to come through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you say, I am breathing in, like, as if you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start doing it, just to become apparent that, yes, you are doing it, and that whole thing is not yours, it's bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything remains the same, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the emphasis of, I am breathing, bodily intention shifts onto the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I am breathing bodily intention, but now it's resting on the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even that I am breathing ceases to be yours, ceases to be mine, ceases to be me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: You become really established, then you go, I'm breathing in like this, I'm breathing in like that, I'll be breathing in like this, I'll be breathing in like that, I'll be feeling this, I'll be feeling that, I'll be doing this, I'll be doing... You can do whatever you like, because none of it belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by practicing it like that, you're just kind of reinforcing that recognition, that it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, it's just in... it's inferior to the whole body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, none of it would be there if that body is not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that body is not intentional to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no intentionality belonging to the body, in regard to the body, none of this would be perceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just that you appropriate intentionality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's mental, belongs... pertains to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said it's much harder... Well, it's easier to see body as not yours and get... get dispassion in regards to it and so on... in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's much harder to... to feel the same towards your mind, because it's subtler, faster, harder to recognize and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mind is inconceivable without the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no consciousness juxtaposed over the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not paired with it,
[SPEAKER_01]: There wouldn't be nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa, just wouldn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why this whole... the elements and body contemplation, just to reveal the subordinate position of the greatest of your thoughts and mind and... Yeah, the mind comes first, in terms of determining things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the order of form being first, structurally, cannot ever change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as an act, for an action, the mind determines it, but structurally speaking, it's all dependent upon this conscious body, like matter that is paired with consciousness out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Conscious matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when you think consciousness, you kind of imply it's inside, on this end of the spectrum, and the matter is out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, both consciousness and the matter are out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your consciousness is there without thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can even... Well, that's why you can perceive distances and space, but above all, that's why you can think in terms of space and in terms of distances, because consciousness is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it goes into infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you can perceive into infinity, if you're able to reach it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea, just the thought of space, will be inconceivable if consciousness is generally inside of you, or in your head, as opposed to the matter out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be just a perfect linear
[SPEAKER_00]: Flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not... Is it one... would you say that it's one presence?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: As many forms as many consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's one, then it's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there are six, which one is yours then?
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are six.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each domain of the senses has its own consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, each particular...
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you have each particular consciousness within the same nature of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all those divisions, like 6, 18, 108, or feelings, or this, or this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not linear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like commentators try to list them all up.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, there is, as an aggregate, as a nature of consciousness, there is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of experience, there's six domains of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's six consciousness, six different consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just recognizing that can be enough for dispassion and abandoning the right view, because if there are six simultaneously present conscious domains, well, none of them, well, certainly not all of them, can be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there is no feeling of singularity, like one, me, there is no feeling of self and mastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there are six, well...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one is it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's this one, yeah, but now it's the other one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: The one that you thought it was yours couldn't be yours, because now the other one is in its place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's six... And then, within each of those domains of consciousness, you have infinite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Infinite structure, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Infinite direction, you can call it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you look at a tree in the distance, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your consciousness is right there, at that distance.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean like your consciousness is there, as if you are here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you walk there, you'll see your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: From your orientation right here, that distance there, the consciousness is out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the extent the distance goes, the extent of the consciousness this goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you wouldn't even perceive that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't even perceive the color or the difference of everything, if it's not manifested there as it is in the distance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if that distance that is just perceived by itself, it's already conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Distance is conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matter is conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just find it all there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the only reason you can actually appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the only reason why the Arahantship is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were not finding it there and appropriating it, you couldn't free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, if you are really creating consciousness and controlling it and directing it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is no gap for any movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all sealed, closed, done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're stuck.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point being, no, there is a mistake going on, which is, you don't see that you already find things already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you misconceive them as mine, as my creation, as I'm the master, as myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what do you find already there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever
[SPEAKER_01]: It has the nature of manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even a fleeting thought, the fact that it has appeared, the fact that you did not... the fact that you just have it appear to you, means it came on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be honest, it's open on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same feeling, intention, anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it appears, means it did not come from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just met it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meeting of the three is contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just met it, ignorantly, and you assumed you were contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you meet it with that understanding, that's... Well, yeah, then you're not contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever, whatever manifests,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already there, given by itself, on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just find it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is nothing else than saying, whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, whatever is manifested, has the nature of manifestation, is in its nature independent of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if something is independent of you, means it comes and goes, and you cannot do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if something is independent of you, it means it is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't obey you, it doesn't listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't take anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see that by default?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm seeing that it's... Yeah, all of these, the experimentation I'm talking about, it's just one insight, very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do not say that there is... that there is the development of mindfulness of breathing for one who is forgetful.
[SPEAKER_00]: For when he contemplates, I shall breathe in contemplating impermanence, contemplating, relinquish, fading away, cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, Abhikābhāna is contemplating mind-objects as mind-objects, having put away covetousness and grief for the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having seen with wisdom the abandonment of covetousness and grief, he closely looks on with equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the occasion Abhikābhāna is contemplating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that having seen it wasn't the abandoning of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows, he sees it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the result is indifference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establishing a minor indifference.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get out, kid.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, the thing is, your mind needs to be quite strong already in order to establish... Yeah, because those are more refined phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, stone or something like that, or body or material things, it's easier to relate to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's how most people inevitably will have to start.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, if your mind gets established upon the thought... Well, you can get established to such a phenomenon, so general, so ambiguous, when you look at it from a daily kind of worldly point of view, like, just say, infinite consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is a real phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you see at the extent that it's present, which is very subtle,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you get established upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you'll be quite skilled in mind establishments, in jhānas and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even further, neither perception or no perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ultimately, cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get established in that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, now when you think about it, infinite consciousness, that thought is in a way that which infinite consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all you have is your own experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, your mind is not trained in regard to that phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you keep dwelling on it long enough, accurately, mindfully, it will become more and more accurate in terms of...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you think infinite consciousness, it will more and more start to stand for that which infinite consciousness really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said before, no matter how abstract thought is, it's abstract only in relation to its content.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, it is very real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because usually, abstract means you dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the nature of abstraction is very real.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the word in the book, infinite consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is already some significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you can designate it, even as an ambiguous abstract term, means there is some significance to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, well, it is experienced in such way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's an idea there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might think infinite consciousness in relation to this present body right here on this chair,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in a way, you can become established upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, after a while, it will become apparent that what you've established is your thought of what Infinite Consciousness is in regard to this body there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's also fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that now, you can see, well, actually, if Infinite Consciousness is what the suttas say Infinite Consciousness is, then there is Infinite Consciousness in regard to my thought, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just in regard to the body there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have infinite consciousness in regard to your thought of what infinite consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, it's much subtler now, already.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nevertheless, if your mind gets skilled in phenomena, in dhamma, you just start seeing these things for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent they appear, you see them for the extent they appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be overcompensating through your ignorance, or you won't be ignoring them through your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be... you'll see them for what they are, to the extent that they have arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's a general thing, you see it as a general thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's a particular thing, you see it as a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be making general into particular, and particular into general, out of your confusion, and over-attending, or under-attending, or mis-attending, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only samanasikāra means that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's having attention that doesn't really... that sees things the way it has arisen, at its root, at its origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's about a subha, putting... seeing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's another step of seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Asubha, like now, you can say, asubha, it can be an abstract term.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, the fact that you were able to designate it, even in such vague, vague terms, means it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you start dwelling on it, and if you dwell on it, you might start seeing more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you might understand the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point being,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, again, when we spoke earlier, learning comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know what you're supposed to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: What... how to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things won't show themselves... show you the truth by themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't... wouldn't need a Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any spiritual teacher would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's all they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you find out what to look for, you start looking for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of a subha, you need to know to look for the aspect of ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beauty is sort of... it's relevant... sorry, it's relative in the same sense that ugliness is relative.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ugly only in relation to something that is less ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, because we get so dependent and attached and infatuated by beauty, you think in terms of beauty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's something ugly, you don't... you really... you might say ugly, but for you, it really means it's less beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's really not beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But beautiful is the reference you think through.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you think through that reference, you're maintaining your sensual dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, view of sensuality, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reminds me of beauty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you see things through beauty, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're not seeing any beautiful objects, you still see them through the beauty, if you're unestablished.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're just seen as less beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you need to do is reverse that, because it's possible, because, again, you can attend it either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is absolutely no reason to attend it as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: No more justified reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason is your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start overriding that, you start overriding your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is the aspect of repulsive in everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that aspect?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the very fact that those things are completely indifferent towards you, independent of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's quite, like, well, especially if you're infatuated, that is quite, well, nice, cool.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you change that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you start looking at everything like that, and then things that seemingly give care for you, you can just see them as, oh, slightly less independent, but still see them through that ugly, ugly aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the infatuation, the criteria of beauty, ceases to be the motivator for your action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you push the door, please?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything can be attended beautifully, or non-beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of habit, you attend everything beautifully, even ugly things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become really skilled in seeing through that dependence, which is what it's meant in those suttas, when the Buddha says, ah, he sees beautiful as ugly, ugly as beautiful, beautiful as beautiful, ugly as ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can do any... either way, his mind is developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Less ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're seeing things as ugly, like even beautiful would be just less ugly, still ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Check this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, really bad-smelling shit, and slightly less-smelling shit, but it's still equally a shit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you wouldn't go and grab a shit because it smells less.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a shit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vice versa.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep seeing it as beautiful, you will go to a very ugly thing, out of despair, and just recognize it as beautiful, attractive, and iceberg, and go for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when there are no beautiful women around, well, you take what you can get.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the standards drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if you're in prison, you go after men that resemble women, or not even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, all through seeing things, through this, like, not being able to break free from dependence, craving for beautiful people.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you reckon it's beautiful and start seeing it as ugly, you will, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's, you know, deeply rooted habit of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it will fade out, because you're not maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if instead of beautiful and less beautiful, you start seeing it as less ugly and ugly, you will get dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a lot like the... yeah, looking at pictures or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it gives you initial spurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't recognize what the actual purpose and the point of the whole thing is, you can be pasting your walls with the super-images.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, after a while, you probably start getting attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be a mutilated corpse, but look at the breasts on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you establish your mind upon the ugly, however, you can have the most gorgeous naked woman right in front of you, inviting you, and you will genuinely not want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be repelled by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is genuinely repelling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually ugly is more fundamental, more structurally, more primordial than beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful requires attraction, and then you start seeing ugly as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get infatuated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ugly doesn't require any... doesn't require passion to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, again, why sensuality is possible to break free from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It quite requires attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires its input.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The power of ugliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though I do not delight in even, what do you call, even a little bit of being, like I do not delight in a little bit of feces.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even like a, you know, a fingernail amount of shit is still shit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Smells like shit, looks like shit.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you taste and taste like shit, that's work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that is, exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or sees independently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indifferent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: For the reason that it has manifested itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the... how to put it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: The key to freedom is in the fact that you're being imprisoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you're in prison means you can be free.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that things arise and you take them as mine and they imprison you the old way, it means that they are not yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can escape, exactly, from their imprisonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the proof in things impermanence is in its manifesting permanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that permanence is manifesting itself by itself, on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, oh, this is impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that very reason, it will... for the reason that it has manifested itself, for that very reason, it will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, its manifestation is its end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shows that end is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But someone could fall... has to go further as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe to think, like I said, I'm free from this now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm free from prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: To notice that freedom is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, people can can reduce that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can get a glimpse or they can read or something and, oh, well, we are already free or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you have to be self-transparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say, oh, yes, I'm free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, okay, well, can the suffering still arise?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just you just bring in another question and criteria and put two and two together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, according to this teaching, they show me the glimpse of this impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free means free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, in all honesty, if I ask myself, can the suffering arise for me, in any form, any shape, whatsoever, in the future, or wherever, can it do so?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see, yes, it means I'm not really free, or not free to the sufficient extent to say I'm free.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I worried about something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you say, but still you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the point of this freedom, if I'm not free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the whole point of freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free from the prospect of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, here and now, in regard to the future, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, I remember when I told you that when I read that, our camera was saying, oh, well, we had already all sought upon this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I was laying there, I realized, I was thinking, wow, so I'm already so dependent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, I thought, well, okay, even if that is true, what difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_01]: If my amount of suffering has not changed, or my amount of being liable to suffering has not changed, what's the point even if I call myself an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless, obviously, you're practicing for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're practicing generally for the freedom from suffering, that becomes the only measure, only criteria you care about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only criteria you should be caring about, because that's what the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only two things, suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the sole purpose, sole taste, absolutely the only thing that his teachings concern about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can think, oh, see, I'm already free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does it affect my suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: My liability to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it feels like it might have helped.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, keep doing it then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes no difference whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep doing it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also the pleasure that comes from jhānas or being secluded from...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something you can crave for.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't really conceive it as a feeling, because... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because feeling now implies... well, because the only pleasure you're familiar with is pleasure of sociality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you withdraw yourself from it sufficiently, then you can discover a different type of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is completely free from underlying tendencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pleasure of jhānas, pleasure of seclusion, pleasure of freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through the subha, you can be knowledge... you see the ugliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reach the dispassion, reach the security from passion, and then feel pleasant on account of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's basically a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was telling you about in chedas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like jhānas, it's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first of all, you see that in ānāpānasati, it's not mentioned at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Leads to four foundations of mindfulness, leads to four powers, leads to seven factors of enlightenment, leads to arhantu.
[SPEAKER_01]: No mention of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because jhāna is a completely different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particularly direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a particular way of establishing yourself as a result of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you reach that dispassion through ānāpānasati, you can establish yourself in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure enough, the suttas say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you reach that dispassion through looking at the subha, you can establish yourself in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you reach that dispassion through thinking about what jhāna is, you can establish yourself in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this whole nonsense, that all came with this premeditating, overmeditating, mismeditating, where you expect, you crave for things, like a hyena looking for a prey, waiting in front of a rabbit hole, and then you have the, you know, transcendental feelings and novelty, bodily experiences, and then, now I'm going to second jhāna, third jhāna, oh yeah, see, now I'm going back to the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's weird.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's a state of quiet seclusion from sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: He dwells, he abides.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abides.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quiet seclusion means he enters and abides in that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then Buddha said, whether you'll be walking in that state, or talking in that state, or sitting in that state, or doing this, his mind remains established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you say in the article and in the Mindfulness of the Body Sutta, it says, when mindfulness is so full, whatever way the water jug, whatever it turns over... Oh, yeah, it goes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to direct your mind to jhāna or whatever, whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to fill it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will go somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how also people develop supernatural powers in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't develop them by kind of doing some special practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They develop mindfulness and then it says, if there was an opening, he recognizes his previous life.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's an opening...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is another way that this mindfulness can be... this jug full of water can be tipped... Because for some people, there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: For some people, there is an opening, and their aggregates allow remembrance of more aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Satipaṭṭhāna...
[SPEAKER_01]: I was just reading that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said he could know nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't see, not even just for one person, the future destination.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't remember anything, none of his future life, none of his previous lives, future destination of people, no deeper job, nothing, nothing, nothing, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't see even a male government.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, he was absolutely the foremost, the marshal of the dhamma, the sutta scholar.
[SPEAKER_01]: After the Buddha, the most supreme in development.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, like, circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people can remember, some people can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have blue eyes, somebody has red... black eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it won't occur to you, if your mindfulness is so full.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your mindfulness is so full, it will manifest itself, if it's... if there is an opening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... you don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see, when they kind of acquire the three, four knowledges, previous lives and everything,
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were committing to the Buddha's instruction, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: They penetrated the truth, they fully realized, and then the knowledge just came, and this came, and then that came, as a result of them fully developing mindfulness to the extent necessary for the five knowledges.
[SPEAKER_01]: The signs of
[SPEAKER_01]: A picture of a sign, don't walk on the grass, is a picture of your absence from that lawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's nimitta, for that sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, for an untrained mind, those nimittas are like, wow, revelation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those are just thoughts in relation to the things that you face through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a super... a super nimitta would just be... A super nimitta would be exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling upon the thought of repulsive in regard to the particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a nimitta in regard... it's a sign and feature of a certain thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when it... the sutra says, when he establishes mindfulness, when things come through his senses, he doesn't give attention to any signs or features.
[SPEAKER_01]: The word is nimitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, when you come across a beautiful science feature, it's sex.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Restraint of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the first nimitta that hits you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you get established upon the repulsive.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to have different significance of that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have different nimittas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have different signs and tokens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Already, we're experiencing nimittas all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, nimitta is just like intentionality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you operate.
[SPEAKER_00]: In many examples, the Buddha goes to see the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: He looks at different parts of his body.
[SPEAKER_00]: He goes to whatever is sort of in the body, like head, testicles, brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those things, all of this, this particular thing, is just reinforcing this aspect, the nature of solidity that is present there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get established in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, okay, well, then there are these things that are not solid.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, less solid is water.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, upon that established aspect, you establish another aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Upon that aspect, you establish another aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, four elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing is not covered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's good to actually go through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean... Yeah, for that reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're expecting some magical nimittas, it's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're either doing it for the utter dispassion in regard to experience as a whole, and then you establish upon that, then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, nimittas will happen, but they won't be mystical kind of manifestations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be like, ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you start recognizing a significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it seemed manifold, this establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like earth, then everything solid, everything watery, everything this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seemed like you're doing the...
[SPEAKER_01]: But after a while, if you keep doing it, if you keep practicing it, that dispassion over things, that becomes a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how manifold was in your doing and intention, when it's being experienced, it's experienced as a single thing, that has its own limiters, that you recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, next time you get those limiters, you get that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get experience, you get those limiters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start recognizing signs and tokens that bring back establishment instantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through the establishing, for example, pondering on the element of earth, the element of earth, you... the more you're established, the more implications that phenomena will reveal, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the more you dwell on the beautiful, the more aspect of beautiful you're gonna get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Warmth, grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You dwell on the indifferent, just like a quite sublime aspect of the earth casino, what you're gonna get?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to get its own significance of earth, of solid, immovable, of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are nimittas in relation to that earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all those things become new ways, new tokens, new signs to bring back the establishment of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, now I have to say woman and the aspect of beauty is back, even if you don't see any particular woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're so familiar and skilled in dwelling on those aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But later on, it will not be for you to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you establish yourself on the casino of earth, you just think solidity, and you establish upon the element of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I'm noticing that it's like... even if form to form, form, it'd be like... and it'd be the entry point to that same... land.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.